Guide to the Rice University scrapbook collection, 1907-1985 UA 230
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series I: Rice Alumni Scrapbooks, 1912 - 1970; 130555
  - Mary Jane Hale Rommel, 1930s; 130802 (Box 21, Item 2)
    Mary Jane Hale Rommel graduated from Rice Institute in 1936. As a junior she was elected to be a maid at the May Fete. She was a member of the Pallas Athene Literary Society. In The Thresher was referred to as the cutest freshman girl. Hale (Rommel) also performed as Maria in the play "Anti-Climax," produced by the Rice Drama Club. Her scrapbook includes many photographs of friends and athletes.
    Separated Materials
    Part of this scrapbook came from the Rice University Association of Alumni Records UA 003.
  - Carolyn Dearmond, 1954 - 1955; 130803 (Box 22, Item 1)
    Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1958 with a B.A. in English. As a freshman she experienced the "rush" for Rice literary societies and became a member of the Owen Wister Literary Society. She was also selected for the freshman court of the Rondelet. She enjoyed attending Rice dances and football games as well as the First Methodist Church. In intramural athletics she competed on the swim team, winning in the 75-yard medley relay and the 50-yard freestyle event. She was selected as a candidate for the 1955 Beauty Section by the Campanile staff.
  - Carolyn Dearmond, 1955 - 1956; 130836 (Box 22, Item 2)
    Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1959 with a B.A. in English. As a sophomore she served as a church school worker for St. Paul's and was a member of the Methodist Student Fellowship of Rice Institute. Dearmond was among 50 candidates for Beauty in the 1956 Yearbook, the Campanile, and she was announced one of the 12 Rice Favorites at the annual Campanile Dance. Dearmond was selected to be on the Rondelet Court in 1956 as a Duchess. She was also a member of the Owen Wister Literary Society, a secretary for the Methodist Student Movement, a member of the Freshman Guidance Council, and a member of the Thresher staff. Dearmond began promoting herself to become a cheerleader next year.
  - Carolyn Dearmond, 1957 - 1958; 130831 (Box 23, Item 1)
    Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1958 with a B.A. in English. Dearmond was Rice's only girl cheerleader and was honored on the Dean's List. She enjoyed following football events and local weddings. She was also selected to represent Rice at the Round-up in Austin and was crowned queen of the Rondelet. Dearmond was on the cover of Houston Adventures, vol. 1 no. 3. She became engaged to Don Caddes, an Electrical Engineering major from Rice. Having competed on the swim team in Rice intramural athletics, she offered a group of ten swimming lessons at Lake Forest Park every summer. After graduation she planned to continue teaching swimming and was employed at the Red Elementary School in Houston.
  - Carolyn Dearmond, 1958 - 1959; 130837 (Box 23, Item 2)
    Carolyn Dearmond graduated from Rice Institute in 1958 with a B.A. in English and began working as a teacher. In the summer of 1958 she married Donald E. Caddes, a fellow Rice student in Electrical Engineering, a member of the Rally Club, and an editor of the Rice Engineer. Caddes was finishing his 5th year of Rice in 1958-1959; thus, this scrapbook still includes Rice-related events, such as Caddes' scholarship and graduation, despite Dearmond having already graduated. Her scrapbook also includes ephemera from local weddings and the Association of Rice Alumni.
  - Dorothy Weiser, 1934 - 1935; 130832 (Box 24, Item 1)
    Dorothy Weiser graduated from Rice Institute in 1937. She was the daughter of Dean Harry B. Weiser and considered one of the most popular co-eds. She was vice president of the Student Association, queen of the May Fete, and a member of the Pallas Athene Literary Society.
  - Dorothy Weiser, 1936 - 1937; 130833 (Box 24, Item 2)
    Dorothy Weiser graduated from Rice Institute in 1937. She was the daughter of Dean Harry B. Weiser and considered one of the most popular co-eds.`She enjoyed following the Rice football team. She participated in the Spring Sport Styles fashion show presented by the Rice Owl. She was a member of the Pallas Athene Literary Society and the lady-in-waiting for Miss Ray Watkin at the Mardi Gras coronation in Galveston. In "A Toast to the Ladies," Weiser was often voted for best face, figure, or date. In this scrapbook there are a few pages of very funny depictions of Weiser, having a photograph of her head attached to various cartoonish bodies.
  - Dorothy Weiser, scrapbook on her Father Dean Harry B. Weiser, n.d.; 130834 (Box 24, Item 3)
    Dorothy Weiser graduated from Rice Institute in 1937. She was the daughter of the Dean of Rice Institute, Dr.Harry Boyer Weiser, and devoted this scrapbook to his success at Rice. Dr. Weiser was also the head of the department of chemistry and was initiated into honorary membership of Alpha Chi Sigma, national chemistry fraternity. He was also a member of the Faraday Society, Phi Beta Kapa, Sixma Xi, Phi Lambda Upsilon, and the American Society for the Advancement of Science. Dr. Weiser was the only Southern chemist on the list of fellows in the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He was also elected to the council of the American Chemical Society as secretary of the division of physical and inorganic chemistry and later as vice-chairman and chairman. He wrote several books on colloidal chemistry and articles for numerous chemical journals, including the Journal of Physical and Colloid Chemistry, of which he became an editor in 1947. On September 1, 1950, Dr. Weiser retired from his role as dean and continued to teach courses in chemistry. Unfortunately, he died soon after on September 27, 1950, at age 63. He was married to Hazel Weiser and had two daughters.
  - Gene Hinyard, Class of 1968 (football), 1949; 130835 (Box 25, Item 1)
    This is a scrapbook of newsclippings about the Rice football team's 1949 season. Among the frequently occurring names are Coach Jess Neely, Tobin Rote, James (Froggie) Williams, Gerald Weatherly, Joe Watson, Gordon Wyatt, Jack Wolcott, Van Ballard, Vernon Glass, and Ralph Murphy.
  - Gene Hinyard, Class of 1968 (football), 1966; 130838 (Box 25, Item 2)
    This is Gene Hinyard's scrapbook of newsclippings about the Rice football team's 1966 season. Inside it but not mounted are several pieces of correspondence re- ferring to his recruitment and signing with Rice. At the beginning is an 8 x 10 black and white photograph of the entire team. Some of the clippings refer to 1966 being Coach Jess Neely's final season at Rice. Included are tributes for his influence on players. Other frequently occurring names are Bobby Shelton, Gene Auldridge, Lester Lehman, L. V. Benningfield, Dan Van Winkle, Frank Mandola, Leland Winston, Chuck Latourette, Robert Hailey, Steve Pritchard, and Harold Bo Hagan, named at the end of the season as Jess Neely's successor as head coach.
  - Gene Hinyard, Class of 1968 (football), 1967; 130839 (Box 25, Item 3)
    Gene Hinyard's scrapbook of newsclippings for the 1967 football season begins with information on the new head coach, Bo Hagan, and his coaching staff. Frequently occurring names of players are Larry Darling, Tommy Tyer, Bobby Shelton, Les Lehman, George Schulgen, Jay Collins, L. V. Benningfield, Dan Van Winkle, Robert Hailey, Pasqual Piedfort, George Alexander, and Hugo Hollas. The last item is an article about the retirement of Cecil Grigg, a longtime assistant coach.
  - Gene Hinyard, Class of 1968 (football), 1968 - 1969; 130840 (Box 25, Item 4)
  - Gene Hinyard, Class of 1968 (football), 160093 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    Gene Hinyard's second 1968 scrapbook of newsclippings covers football games of the conference season. Included are articles containing Coach Bo Hagan's analyses of one loss after another. A photograph of five homecoming queen candidates documents existence of a traditional queen crowning at halftime during the homecoming football game. Names of stand-out players include Bucky Allshouse, who was called on as a sophomore to replace an injured punter; Gene Taubert; Bobby (also using the name Robby) Shelton; Roger Roitsch; and Leland Winston.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1947-1948; 130841 (Box 26, Item 1)
    The content is a thorough collection of newsclippings about a wide range of activities, people, and events associated with Rice in the academic year 1947-48. The activities include athletic contests in a variety of sports, social occasions, weddings, and once-a-year occurrences like the Archi-Arts Ball and an operetta performed at Autry House. The people represented are members of the class of '48; Rice alumni; faculty like the English professor newly hired away from Harvard, Dr. William S. Dix; and distinguished scholars coming to speak at Rice. The events covered include construction of Anderson Hall and Fondren Library and a series of public lectures offered by Rice faculty on Sunday afternoons. The final page is a group of articles covering the death of Trustee Harry C. Wiess at age 61.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1951-1952; 130842 (Box 26, Item 2)
    The content is a thorough collection of newsclippings about a wide range of activities, people, and events associated with Rice from fall 1952 to commencement 1953. The activities include athletic contests in a variety of sports, individuals' weddings, and homecoming of both 1951 and 1952. A photograph documents the 15-year reunion of the 1937 Southwest Conference and Cotton Bowl football champions. A musical show called "Campusology" was performed in the San Jacinto auditorium. People featured in addition to class members whose marriages were announced include Mrs. Harry C. Wiess, to whom a Distinguished Service to Rice award was presented; Religion Professor Dr. Niels C. Nielsen; Bursar J. T. McCants retiring after 43 years at Rice; Nell Harris Swartz, an alumna who founded Hedgecroft Clinic for polio victims, because of dedication of its addition; Roy Hofheinz, Jr. about to enter Rice after winning top scholastic award at Lamar High School; James Chillman of the Rice Architecture Department, retiring from duties as curator of the Houston Museum of Fine Arts; Dr. Hubert E. Bray, Professor of Mathematics and president of the Southwest Con- ference; Dr. Carey Croneis, named as head of the new Geology Department and Provost; James C. Morehead of the Architecture Department, featured for designing a new suburban home; and alumnus and novelist David Westheimer returning to the Houston Post. Events featured in this scrapbook include the acquisition of an important micro- film collection by Fondren Library; acquisition of an electron microscope, the first to be installed in the Houston area and owned jointly by Rice and Humble Oil; the $1,570,000 gift to Rice by Mrs. Olga Keith Wiess in memory of Harry C. Wiess, an endowment which would make possible Rice's first teaching and research in geology; the 13th Biennial Review of Science and the Arts, a project of exhibits for the public; publication of the Rice students' book Soundings (160 pages, Anson Jones Press, $3); Rice Day, an event for Rice alumni and students that included athletic activities and a scene from the faculty operetta Iolanthe; and Rice and the University of Houston signing a 10-year pact for joint use of the football stadium.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1946-1947; 130843 (Box 27, Item 1)
    The content is a collection of newsclippings about people, activities, and events asso- ciated with Rice during the 1946-47 academic year. There are many announcements of engagements and marriages, as well as reports of athletic contests in several sports. Receiving especially bold attention are the Oct. 6, 1946, football victory, 18 to 13, over The University of Texas with 31,000 people attending, and the Jan. 1, 1947, victory, 8 to 0, over Tennessee in the Orange Bowl. A number of articles have to do with the inauguration of Rice's second president, Dr. W. V. Houston, on April 10, 1947. Included is one of the official programs for the event. Occasioned by the inauguration is a long Houston Chronicle article detailing the story of William Marsh Rice's murder and the resulting trials. The people featured include Mrs. Ella A. Fondren on the occasion of her $1 million gift for construction of the library building and Mr. and Mrs. Harry C. Wiess for giving $1 million designated to expand science and engineering work. An article covers the appointment of four new faculty, Dr. Hardin Craig, history; Dr. James Street Fulton, philosophy; Dr. James Treanor Smith, chemistry; and Dr. Andrew Louis, German. Another article covers retirements of Rice's first four emeriti, Dr. Harold Albert Wilson, physics; Dr. J. W. Slaughter, sociology; Alice Crowell Dean, librarian and mathematics; and Dr. Max Friedrich Ernest Freund, German.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1948-1949; 130844 (Box 27, Item 2)
    The content is a collection of newsclippings about people, activities, and events asso- ciated with Rice during the 1948-49 academic year. Events include the annual dinner of Rice Institute Alumni, at which were honored the first four faculty members to reach emeritus status, Miss Alice Dean, Dr. John W. Slaughter, Dr. Harold A. Wilson, and Dr. Max Freund. Also covered is what is described as the annual Rice Day, April 30, 1949. An article features preparations for moving books into the new Fondren Library in the fall, and another is about completion of the new president's house on campus (at a cost of $100,000). Activities include plans for homecoming Nov. 18-20, the 1949 Archi-Arts Ball, and the Third Annual Rondelet Ball on May 7, sponsored by the Rice Women's Council and replacing the pre-war May fetes. There is especially full pictorial coverage of the Archi-Arts Ball, which had Sargasso as its theme. There were 10 honorees costumed to represent famous rivers of the world. An article announces the first complete entrance of women students into sports instruction and competition. There are also features on the Rice ROTC and on Autry House as the center for a wide range of student activities. An article covers Dr. Charles Squire of physics, named as head of a new low temperature lab, and the type of research for which the lab is planned. Another article reports Don Suman taking over as head basketball coach.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1953; 130845 (Box 28, Item 1)
    The content is a very thorough collection of newsclippings about activities, people, and events associated with Rice from July of 1953 through July of 1954. Athletics figure prominently in the activities covered. The teams that stand out are football, predicted to be the best since 1949, and basketball. The football team was Southwest Conference champion and played Jan. 1, 1954, in the Cotton Bowl. The basketball team was Southwest Conference co-champion. Dickie Moegle was one of the stand-out football players. Other noteworthy activities were the Archi-Arts Ball, Rondelet, Rice Day (described as the student-alumni spring homecoming), and the Second Shakespearean Fete. The theme of the well-photographed Archi-Arts Ball was The Neon Hours—the city at night.
    There was press coverage of Philosophy Professor Dr. R. Tsanoff twice, once for a speech on intellectual freedom and in a rotogravure section story titled "Don't Sell Our Youth Short." Sandy Havens is announced to be one of two student co- ordinators of Rice Players. An article features Board of Governors member Herbert Allen, described as having begun his career as an inventor while a student At Rice. The long career of J. T. McCants at Rice is covered on the occasion of his retirement. He began in 1910 as secretary to President Lovett, and subsequently taught English, business administration, and money and banking before be- coming bursar. Other noteworthy individuals covered are Dr. Carey Croneis, who arrived to become the provost and to head the Wiess School of Geology, and James Dickey, who was briefly an instructor in English (but became a nationally- known poet and novelist).
    Coverage of events begins with the July 17, 1953, crash of a marine cargo plane killing ten Rice Naval ROTC men and seriously injuring one. Announcement is made of plans to open the Hillel Center at Rice. 1953 is the year that the bronze bust of Gertrude Stein by Jacques Lipschitz was presented to Rice by Mrs. Kenneth Dale Owen. The International Conference of Low Temperature Physics and Chemistry was held at Rice, significant because of being the first time this meeting was held in the U.S. On April 2 and 3, 1954, the 14th Biennial Exposi- tion of Engineering and the Arts took place. The final noteworthy event covered was the first annual dinner for Rice Associates, which 180 guests attended.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, pre - 1941; 130846 (Box 29, Item 1)
    The content is newsclippings, many loose but some mounted in the book. The listing that follows is chronological. Earliest is a 12-page special section of the Houston Chronicle dated Oct. 22, 1932, celebrating the twenty-first anniversary of Rice. Next are four 1935 newsclippings concerning the Nov. 16 football game between Rice and Texas A and M, which Rice won 17 to 10. Twelve 1936 items concern the home- coming festivities Nov. 20-22. Combined with homecoming was celebration of the 25th anniversary of the founding of the university. Four members of the original faculty were to be seated at the head table of the Friday Nov. 20 dinner: Dr. Lovett, John T. McCants, William Ward Watkin, and Harold Albert Wilson. A Dec. 24, 1936 article announces the gift to Rice from William Marsh Rice, Jr., of $320,000.
    Nov. 7 – 12, 1937, articles concern homecoming. A Nov. 13 item reports presentation to William Marsh Rice, Jr., of a gold medal for distinguished service to Rice by the president of Rice alumni.
    The only 1938 item is from April 27 about the Rice Alumni Association honoring the stadium committee on the occasion of raising $204,000.
    A June 9, 1941, article covers commencement, and from Sunday June 22 there is a full rotogravure page with pictures of graduates from the first classes, 1916, 1917, and 1918. The occasion was the 25th anniversary of the first commence- ment.
    A large envelope contains items from 1941, 1943, and 1945. An Aug. 7, 1941 article announces that William Marsh Rice, Jr. has been elected president of the board trustees. An article of Nov. 6, 1941, is about events associated with home- coming. Nov. 8 items report actions of the Alumni Association: the presentation of the second gold medal for distinguished service to Rice to Dr. Lovett, and the election of Harvin C. Moore as its president. Also in this envelope are two copies of the Nov. 11, 1943 Thresher and a Nov. 24, 1945 article from a Ft. Worth paper anticipating the annual Rice-T.C.U. football game.
  - Association of Rice Alumni Scrapbook, 1955; 130847 (Box 29, Item 2)
    The content is a collection of newsclippings about activities, events, and people associated with Rice during the 1954-55 school year. Coverage of athletic teams and engagements and marriages dominates the collection, but there are a number of additional noteworthy particular items.
    Activities of note include the opening Rice football game against Florida, at which attendance was expected to be 40,000, and which Rice won 34-14, and the annual Archi-Arts Ball with the theme "The Universe of the Future" and eight women honorees. At Autry House the Pallas Athena Literary Society presented their annual burlesque, "Tsk Tsk (All About Women)." The Rice Players pre- sented Eliot's Murder in the Cathedral and Earth Spirit by Frank Wederkind (in the Fondren Library exam room).
    Events include the Nov. 21, 1954 Fall Lecture by Mr. C. M. Class, "Recent Advances in Nuclear Science", the setting of four relief sculpture tablets into the entrance pillars of the Chemistry Building, and the opening of a center for Catholic Rice students, the Maryheart Newman Center. Commencement on June 3, 1955, for which Sen. J William Fulbright was the speaker, was marked by the conferring of the first geology degrees and the first Ph.D in any kind of engineering.
    People covered include Charles F. Jones, William Marsh Rice's slayer, who killed himself in his Baytown house; Jack Heard, who played football at Rice, becoming Houston Chief of Police; Representative Albert Thomas, who started at Rice but had his studies interrupted by World War I; Dr. Tom Bonner, head of the physics department, for his research using the Van de Graaff atom smasher; Oren Arnold, alumnus and novelist, for winning the first Elsevier Southwest Literary Award; wife of English Prof. A. D. McKillop for her repeated lectures on old English silver; Ervin Frederick ("Tiny") Kalb, graduate of the first class, for his work raising funds from alumni; Dr. Roy Talmage, professor of biology, receiving a grant for his armadillo research; Dr. Frank Vandiver, appointed assistant professor of history; Joe Frank, alumnus, for his nationally known women's high fashion business; English Professors Carroll Camden and George Williams, featured in article about Texas writers; David Westheimer, alumnus and writer, whose entire article, "The Non-Television Part of Texas Is shrinking Apace," is included; Mason Lockwood, alumnus, chosen Engineer of the Year in Houston; Dr. B.B. Hudson and Dr. W. H. Masterson promoted to full professor; Sandy Havens, praised for his role in Univ. of Houston production of Androcles and the Lion; Dickey Moegle, drafted by the San Francisco '49ers and also offered a movie contract; Joan and Jane Ryba, twin Rice cheerleaders, named queen of the Auto Show.
  - Alumni Association, 1958; 130848 (Box 30, Item 1)
    The content is a collection of newsclippings about people, events, and activities associated with Rice from July 1955 to January 1959. The collection is dominated by coverage of athletic teams, games, engagements, and marriages, but the compilers were thorough in including a great deal that was covered about Rice in the newspapers.